<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Papers on Tao Ruyi&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:55717/papers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Papers on Tao Ruyi&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 17:29:42 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:55717/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Data driven modeling for self-similar dynamics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:55717/papers/self_similar_dy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 17:29:42 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:55717/papers/self_similar_dy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Multiscale modeling of complex systems is crucial for understanding their intricacies. In recent years, data-driven multiscale modeling has emerged as a promising approach to tackle challenges associated with complex systems. Still, at present,this field is more focused on the prediction or control problems in specific fields, and there is no suitable framework to help us promote the establishment of complex system modeling theory. On the other hand, self-similarity is prevalent in complex systems, hinting that large-scale complex systems can be modeled at a reduced cost. In this paper, we introduce a multiscale neural network framework that incorporates self-similarity as prior knowledge, facilitating the modeling of self-similar dynamical systems. Our framework can discern whether the dynamics are self-similar to deterministic dynamics. For uncertain dynamics, it not only can judge whether it is self-similar or not, but also can compare and determine which parameter set is closer to self-similarity. The framework allows us to extract scale-invariant kernels from the dynamics for modeling at any scale. Moreover, our method can identify the power-law exponents in self-similar systems, providing valuable insights for the establishment of complex system modeling theory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Prediction Framework of Company Growth Based Scaling Law and Neural Network</title>
      <link>http://localhost:55717/papers/company_prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 17:29:42 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:55717/papers/company_prediction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Predicting company growth carries significant implications for strategic adjustment, operational decision-making, risk assessment, and loan eligibility reviews. Traditional attempts to model company growth either overly focus on theory, neglecting practical forecasting, or rely on time-series forecasting techniques without incorporating the inherent mechanisms of corporate growth. A recent study established a first-principles growth model for enterprises based on scaling laws, providing predictions superior to baseline methods regarding average business growth. In this paper, we propose a hybrid prediction framework for company growth, blending the growth equation of enterprises with time-series forecasting technology. Specifically, we used a neural network model as a prediction method to make our framework more extensible.  This model captures both the intrinsic growth mechanisms of enterprises and the fluctuations in the external environment, demonstrating superior predictive performance compared to methods using time-series forecasting technology alone. Moreover, we found that the advantages of our framework are more prominent for long-range prediction tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
