<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Papers on Tao Ruyi's Blog</title><link>https://try6.github.io/papers/</link><description>Recent content in Papers on Tao Ruyi's Blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 16:02:12 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://try6.github.io/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dynamical reversibility and a new theory of causal emergence based on SVD</title><link>https://try6.github.io/papers/dy_reversibility/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 16:02:12 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/papers/dy_reversibility/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44260-025-00028-0">[link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jiang Zhang, &lt;strong>Ruyi Tao&lt;/strong>, Keng Hou Leong, Mingzhe Yang, Bing Yuan, 2025&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The theory of causal emergence (CE) with effective information (EI) posits that complex systems can exhibit CE, where macro-dynamics show stronger causal effects than micro-dynamics. A key challenge of this theory is its dependence on coarse-graining method. In this paper, we introduce a fresh concept of approximate dynamical reversibility derived from the singular value decomposition(SVD) of the Markov chain and establish a novel framework for CE based on this. We find that the essence of CE lies in the presence of redundancy, represented by irreversible and correlated information pathways within the Markov dynamics. Therefore, CE can be quantified as the potential maximal efficiency increase for dynamical reversibility or information transmission. We also demonstrate a strong correlation between the approximate dynamical reversibility and EI, establishing an equivalence between the SVD and EI maximization frameworks for quantifying CE, supported by theoretical insights and numerical examples from Boolean networks, cellular automata, and complex networks. Importantly, our SVD-based CE framework is independent of specific coarse-graining techniques and effectively captures the fundamental characteristics of the dynamics.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data driven modeling for self-similar dynamics</title><link>https://try6.github.io/papers/self_similar_dy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 17:29:42 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/papers/self_similar_dy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S016727892400455X">[link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Ruyi Tao&lt;/strong>, Ningning Tao, Yi-zhuang You, Jiang Zhang, 2025&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Multiscale modeling of complex systems is crucial for understanding their intricacies. In recent years, data-driven multiscale modeling has emerged as a promising approach to tackle challenges associated with complex systems. Still, at present,this field is more focused on the prediction or control problems in specific fields, and there is no suitable framework to help us promote the establishment of complex system modeling theory. On the other hand, self-similarity is prevalent in complex systems, hinting that large-scale complex systems can be modeled at a reduced cost. In this paper, we introduce a multiscale neural network framework that incorporates self-similarity as prior knowledge, facilitating the modeling of self-similar dynamical systems. Our framework can discern whether the dynamics are self-similar to deterministic dynamics. For uncertain dynamics, it not only can judge whether it is self-similar or not, but also can compare and determine which parameter set is closer to self-similarity. The framework allows us to extract scale-invariant kernels from the dynamics for modeling at any scale. Moreover, our method can identify the power-law exponents in self-similar systems, providing valuable insights for the establishment of complex system modeling theory.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hybrid Prediction Framework of Company Growth Based Scaling Law and Neural Network</title><link>https://try6.github.io/papers/company_prediction/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 17:29:42 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/papers/company_prediction/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/BvD-oBcfVwCTCs3L8zFijQ">[link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Ruyi Tao&lt;/strong>, Kaiwei Liu, Jing Xu, Jiang Zhang, 2025&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Predicting company growth carries significant implications for strategic adjustment, operational decision-making, risk assessment, and loan eligibility reviews. Traditional attempts to model company growth either overly focus on theory, neglecting practical forecasting, or rely on time-series forecasting techniques without incorporating the inherent mechanisms of corporate growth. A recent study established a first-principles growth model for enterprises based on scaling laws, providing predictions superior to baseline methods regarding average business growth. In this paper, we propose a hybrid prediction framework for company growth, blending the growth equation of enterprises with time-series forecasting technology. Specifically, we used a neural network model as a prediction method to make our framework more extensible. This model captures both the intrinsic growth mechanisms of enterprises and the fluctuations in the external environment, demonstrating superior predictive performance compared to methods using time-series forecasting technology alone. Moreover, we found that the advantages of our framework are more prominent for long-range prediction tasks.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Graph Completion Through Local Pattern Generalization</title><link>https://try6.github.io/papers/network_complete/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 06:37:01 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/papers/network_complete/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44260-025-00028-0">[link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Zhang Zhang, &lt;strong>Ruyi Tao&lt;/strong>, Yongzai Tao, Mingze Qi &amp;amp; Jiang Zhang, 2024&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>