<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Tao Ruyi&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://try6.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Tao Ruyi&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 17:29:42 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://try6.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Data driven modeling for self-similar dynamics</title>
      <link>http://try6.github.io/posts/02self_similar_dy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 17:29:42 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://try6.github.io/posts/02self_similar_dy/</guid>
      <description>Multiscale modeling of complex systems is crucial for understanding their intricacies. In recent years, data-driven multiscale modeling has emerged as a promising approach to tackle challenges associated with complex systems. Still, at present,this field is more focused on the prediction or control problems in specific fields, and there is no suitable framework to help us promote the establishment of complex system modeling theory. On the other hand, self-similarity is prevalent in complex systems, hinting that large-scale complex systems can be modeled at a reduced cost.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Renormalization Group Meets Machine Learning</title>
      <link>http://try6.github.io/posts/03rg_ml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 17:29:42 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://try6.github.io/posts/03rg_ml/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Law</title>
      <link>http://try6.github.io/posts/scaling_law/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 17:31:02 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://try6.github.io/posts/scaling_law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-scaling-law&#34;&gt;What is Scaling law&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists always expect to summarize the unified laws of the complex world. Physicists have come a long way in search of basic laws. As early as the 17th century, Kepler summarized the three major laws of planetary motion from Tycho&amp;rsquo;s astronomical observational data. However, for the complexity science, everything is just beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subject of complexity science is complex systems, and there is currently no perfect unified theory that encompasses all complex systems. However, there exists a theory with such potential, whether it is the richly diverse life system, cities with various forms around the world, or seemingly random economic systems, they all have a unified form of characterization —- this is the scaling law.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Prediction Framework of Company Growth Based Scaling Law and Neural Network</title>
      <link>http://try6.github.io/posts/01comapny_prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 17:29:42 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://try6.github.io/posts/01comapny_prediction/</guid>
      <description>Predicting company growth carries significant implications for strategic adjustment, operational decision-making, risk assessment, and loan eligibility reviews. Traditional attempts to model company growth either overly focus on theory, neglecting practical forecasting, or rely on time-series forecasting techniques without incorporating the inherent mechanisms of corporate growth. A recent study established a first-principles growth model for enterprises based on scaling laws, providing predictions superior to baseline methods regarding average business growth. In this paper, we propose a hybrid prediction framework for company growth, blending the growth equation of enterprises with time-series forecasting technology.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
