<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Publication on Tao Ruyi's Blog</title><link>https://try6.github.io/publications/</link><description>Recent content in Publication on Tao Ruyi's Blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://try6.github.io/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Data driven modeling for self-similar dynamics</title><link>https://try6.github.io/publications/self_similar_dy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/publications/self_similar_dy/</guid><description>&lt;p>Multiscale modeling of complex systems is crucial for understanding their intricacies. In recent years, data-driven multiscale modeling has emerged as a promising approach to tackle challenges associated with complex systems. Still, at present,this field is more focused on the prediction or control problems in specific fields, and there is no suitable framework to help us promote the establishment of complex system modeling theory. On the other hand, self-similarity is prevalent in complex systems, hinting that large-scale complex systems can be modeled at a reduced cost. In this paper, we introduce a multiscale neural network framework that incorporates self-similarity as prior knowledge, facilitating the modeling of self-similar dynamical systems. Our framework can discern whether the dynamics are self-similar to deterministic dynamics. For uncertain dynamics, it not only can judge whether it is self-similar or not, but also can compare and determine which parameter set is closer to self-similarity. The framework allows us to extract scale-invariant kernels from the dynamics for modeling at any scale. Moreover, our method can identify the power-law exponents in self-similar systems, providing valuable insights for the establishment of complex system modeling theory.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dynamical reversibility and a new theory of causal emergence based on SVD</title><link>https://try6.github.io/publications/dy_reversibility/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/publications/dy_reversibility/</guid><description>&lt;p>The theory of causal emergence (CE) with effective information (EI) posits that complex systems can exhibit CE, where macro-dynamics show stronger causal effects than micro-dynamics. A key challenge of this theory is its dependence on coarse-graining method. In this paper, we introduce a fresh concept of approximate dynamical reversibility derived from the singular value decomposition(SVD) of the Markov chain and establish a novel framework for CE based on this. We find that the essence of CE lies in the presence of redundancy, represented by irreversible and correlated information pathways within the Markov dynamics. Therefore, CE can be quantified as the potential maximal efficiency increase for dynamical reversibility or information transmission. We also demonstrate a strong correlation between the approximate dynamical reversibility and EI, establishing an equivalence between the SVD and EI maximization frameworks for quantifying CE, supported by theoretical insights and numerical examples from Boolean networks, cellular automata, and complex networks. Importantly, our SVD-based CE framework is independent of specific coarse-graining techniques and effectively captures the fundamental characteristics of the dynamics.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Graph Completion Through Local Pattern Generalization</title><link>https://try6.github.io/publications/network_complete/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/publications/network_complete/</guid><description>&lt;p>Network completion is more challenging than link prediction, as it aims to infer both missing links and nodes. Although various methods exist for this problem, few utilize structural information-specifically, the similarity of local connection patterns. In this study, we introduce a model called C-GIN, which captures local structural patterns in the observed portions of a network using a Graph Auto-Encoder equipped with a Graph Isomorphism Network. This model generalizes these patterns to complete the entire graph. Experimental results on both synthetic and real-world networks across diverse domains indicate that C-GIN not only requires less information but also outperforms baseline prediction models in most cases. Additionally, we propose a metric known as “Reachable Clustering Coefficient (RCC)” based on network structure. Experiments reveal that C-GIN performs better on networks with higher Reachable CC values.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hybrid Prediction Framework of Company Growth Based Scaling Law and Neural Network</title><link>https://try6.github.io/publications/company_prediction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/publications/company_prediction/</guid><description>&lt;p>Predicting company growth carries significant implications for strategic adjustment, operational decision-making, risk assessment, and loan eligibility reviews. Traditional attempts to model company growth either overly focus on theory, neglecting practical forecasting, or rely on time-series forecasting techniques without incorporating the inherent mechanisms of corporate growth. A recent study established a first-principles growth model for enterprises based on scaling laws, providing predictions superior to baseline methods regarding average business growth. In this paper, we propose a hybrid prediction framework for company growth, blending the growth equation of enterprises with time-series forecasting technology. Specifically, we used a neural network model as a prediction method to make our framework more extensible. This model captures both the intrinsic growth mechanisms of enterprises and the fluctuations in the external environment, demonstrating superior predictive performance compared to methods using time-series forecasting technology alone. Moreover, we found that the advantages of our framework are more prominent for long-range prediction tasks.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scaling laws and a general theory for the growth of public companies</title><link>https://try6.github.io/publications/company_scaling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://try6.github.io/publications/company_scaling/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publicly traded companies are fundamental units of contemporary economies and markets and are important mechanisms through which humans interact with their environments. Understanding the general properties that underlie the processes of their growth has long been of interest, yet fundamental debates about the effects of firm size on growth have persisted. Here we develop a scaling framework that focuses on company size as the critical feature determining a variety of tradeoffs, and use this to reveal novel systematic behavior across the diversity of publicly-traded companies. Using a large database of 31,553 US companies over nearly 70 years, and 3,160 Chinese companies over 24 year, we show how the dynamics of companies expressed as scaling relationships leads to a quantitative, analytic theory for their growth. This theory produces several predictions that are in good agreement with data for both the US and China, whose markets have strikingly different histories and underlying structures. In both cases sales scale sublinearly with assets and exhibit nearly identical exponents leading, surprisingly and nontrivially, to assets that grow as a power law in time rather than exponentially, as often assumed. On the other hand, liabilities scale linearly in the US (exponent of 1.0) but superlinearly in China (exponent of 1.09). We show that such small differences in scaling exponents can have a significant impact on the character and long-term evolution of growth trajectories. These results illustrate that while companies are part of a larger class
of growth phenomena driven by incomes and costs that scale with size, they are unique in that they grow following a temporal power-function which sets them apart from organisms, cities, nations, and markets, whose growth over time is often exponential. The perspective developed here highlights novel dynamics in the scaling and growth of human economies.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>